<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-08-11T00:35:02+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Brian Kibet Portfolio</title><subtitle>A portfolio showcasing my work, skills, and thoughts - some structured, some spontaneous, some random.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Strength of Being Misunderstood</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025-08-9-The-Strength-of-Being-Misunderstood/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Strength of Being Misunderstood" /><published>2025-08-09T01:21:57+03:00</published><updated>2025-08-09T01:21:57+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/The-Strength-of-Being-Misunderstood</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025-08-9-The-Strength-of-Being-Misunderstood/"><![CDATA[<p>Almost everyone cares what someone thinks (though caring what everyone thinks is definitely a mistake), and it’s probably important. Caring too much makes you a sheep. But you need to be at least a little in tune with others to do something useful for them. It seems like there are two degrees of freedom: you can choose the people whose opinions you care about (and on what subjects), and you can choose the timescale you care about them on. Most people figure out the former [1] but the latter doesn’t seem to get much attention.
The most impressive people I know care a lot about what people think, even people whose opinions they really shouldn’t value (a surprising numbers of them do something like keeping a folder of screenshots of tweets from haters). But what makes them unusual is that they generally care about other people’s opinions on a very long time horizon—as long as the history books get it right, they take some pride in letting the newspapers get it wrong.
You should trade being short-term low-status for being long-term high-status, which most people seem unwilling to do. A common way this happens is by eventually being right about an important but deeply non-consensus bet. But there are lots of other ways–the key observation is that as long as you are right, being misunderstood by most people is a strength not a weakness. You and a small group of rebels get the space to solve an important problem that might otherwise not get solved.</p>

<p><a href="https://blog.samaltman.com/the-strength-of-being-misunderstood" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sam Altman</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Being" /><category term="misunderstood" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The key observation is that as long as you are right, being misunderstood by most people is a strength not a weakness.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beyond Smart</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025-08-9-Beyond-Smart/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond Smart" /><published>2025-08-09T01:21:57+03:00</published><updated>2025-08-09T01:21:57+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Beyond-Smart</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025-08-9-Beyond-Smart/"><![CDATA[<p>If you asked people what was special about Einstein, most would say that he was really smart. Even the ones who tried to give you a more sophisticated-sounding answer would probably think this first. Till a few years ago I would have given the same answer myself. But that wasn’t what was special about Einstein. What was special about him was that he had important new ideas. Being very smart was a necessary precondition for having those ideas, but the two are not identical. It may seem a hair-splitting distinction to point out that intelligence and its consequences are not identical, but it isn’t. There’s a big gap between them. Anyone who’s spent time around universities and research labs knows how big. There are a lot of genuinely smart people who don’t achieve very much.
I grew up thinking that being smart was the thing most to be desired. Perhaps you did too. But I bet it’s not what you really want. Imagine you had a choice between being really smart but discovering nothing new, and being less smart but discovering lots of new ideas. Surely you’d take the latter. I would. The choice makes me uncomfortable, but when you see the two options laid out explicitly like that, it’s obvious which is better.
The reason the choice makes me uncomfortable is that being smart still feels like the thing that matters, even though I know intellectually that it isn’t. I spent so many years thinking it was. The circumstances of childhood are a perfect storm for fostering this illusion. Intelligence is much easier to measure than the value of new ideas, and you’re constantly being judged by it. Whereas even the kids who will ultimately discover new things aren’t usually discovering them yet. For kids that way inclined, intelligence is the only game in town.
There are more subtle reasons too, which persist long into adulthood. Intelligence wins in conversation, and thus becomes the basis of the dominance hierarchy. [1] Plus having new ideas is such a new thing historically, and even now done by so few people, that society hasn’t yet assimilated the fact that this is the actual destination, and intelligence merely a means to an end. [2]
Why do so many smart people fail to discover anything new? Viewed from that direction, the question seems a rather depressing one. But there’s another way to look at it that’s not just more optimistic, but more interesting as well. Clearly intelligence is not the only ingredient in having new ideas. What are the other ingredients? Are they things we could cultivate?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.paulgraham.com/smart.html\" target="_blank\" rel="noopener noreferrer">Paul Graham</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Beyond" /><category term="smart" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post explores the concept of intelligence beyond traditional metrics.]]></summary></entry></feed>